<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The True narrative of the confession and execution of Thomas Pardue, a notorious housebreaker, at Tyburn on Fryday the 25th of this instant June 1680 with the manner of his behaviour in prison since his condemnation : as likewise several particulars concerning Robert Gale, broker.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63565</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2781A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27146</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09677399</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09677399</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43959</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63565)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43959)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1344:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The True narrative of the confession and execution of Thomas Pardue, a notorious housebreaker, at Tyburn on Fryday the 25th of this instant June 1680 with the manner of his behaviour in prison since his condemnation : as likewise several particulars concerning Robert Gale, broker.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pardue, Thomas, d. 1680?</term>
               <term>Executions and executioners --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:43959:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:43959:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->
            <head>THE TRUE NARRATIVE OF THE CONFESSION AND EXECUTION Of <hi>Thomas Pardue,</hi> a notorious Houſebreaker, at TYBURN. <date>On <hi>Fryday</hi> the 25th of this inſtant <hi>June</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</date>
            </head>
            <p>With the manner of his Behaviour in Priſon ſince his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
            <p>As likewiſe ſeveral particulars concerning <hi>Robe<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Gale</hi> Broker.</p>
            <p>SO powerful a Temptation is pernicious Wealth unto the Covetous mind, and thirſt of Gain ſo Charms their Senſes that as a Lethargy it quite overſpreads their Reaſon till ſtupefied at ſuch a Rate, as Men not well knowing what they do for if they did, 'tis ſure they would be more cautious of their ſafety, than to run headlong upon the fatal Piles of Ruine and deſtruction not minding the cloſe ſnares of Death layed to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap their haſty Feet ſtop them in their full Career, nor thoſe prying Anticks Fate has ſet in the broad way that leads to deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and the Gaſtly Courts where horror dwells, but blinded with the vain hopes of ſafety and eſcape; they boaſt of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturous Raſhneſs or pernicious Fully even on the brink of vaſt Eternity and Gap of ſeparation from this mortal Life, and ſmile diſdainfully upon the upon the Glittering Sword that angry Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice draws to cut them off and make them ceaſe to be on Earth,
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:43959:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->as almoſt Monthly examples though various in effects can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the World, of which number this we now ſhall treat of is not the leaſt for all deſperate minded wretches to have rega<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d unto and be forewarned by timely preventing the ſelfsame fate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Pardue</hi> a notorious Offendor, whoſe many Crimes and Villanous exploits would be too many to repeat in this ſmall. Tract, therefore we only ſhall make mention of thoſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar or which he was Arraigned Condemned, and now Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Followeths. Firſt, for that he in the Company of <hi>John Bigs, J<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hn E<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ias, J<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hn Ralphs, Clement Snell,</hi> already Executed, committed a Robbery upon the houſe of Mr. <hi>Benning</hi> of <hi>Wilſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> in the County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> who living in a houſe ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from Neighbours, this Gang h<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d intelligence by their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſar<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or Scouts that he was a rich Man, and always kept good ſtore of Plate and Monies in his houſe, and farther, that at ſuch a tune he was to be at <hi>London,</hi> and that he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue there all night, with a relation of all the Room and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient places for hiding and concealing mony, plate, or ſuch like, which they at that time pretended much to want, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they had a Cuſtomer, for ſuch commodities, who had been lately with them, and were very importunate for them to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed upon ſome enterprize of great worth, ſo that according to their intelligence they went, and by lying in a Wood which was in ſight of the houſe, conducted thither by one <hi>Evans</hi> yet in <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> they could plainly diſcern who paſſed in or out of the houſe ſo that long they had not lain in Ambuſh before they ſaw Mr. <hi>Benning</hi> take <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orſe for <hi>London,</hi> upon which they concluded, all the reſt that they had been informed was true; whereupon, as ſoon as it was dark, three of them went and knocked at the Dore, whereupon the Maid of the Houſe asked who was there, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied Friends ſo that the Maid thinking they had been Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, opened the Dore, which being no ſooner done, but they ruſhed in violently, and held open the Dore till the reſt of their Gang came in, ſo that all being enterred, they bound the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſiſting of four perſons, the Miſtreſs of the houſe two men and the Maid, but upon ſecond thoughts they looſed the Maid, to ſhew them the Rooms, and light them the Candle, whilſt they plundered, ſo that having ſearched what places they pleaſed, they did not much fail in their expectations, for in monies and Plate, they got to the vallue of 250 pound, after that they compelled
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43959:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->the Maid to fetch them what Victuals there was in the houſe, and ſat down at the Table, and there drinking ſeveral healths, they took their fatal repaſt for the ſpace of four hours or thereabouts and then departed, with their Booty, and glad of ſo rich a prize, which exceeded their expectations, but as this Priſoner reported <hi>Evan:</hi> who impeached them, was not actually in the Robery, but upon ſome diſtaſte, or through fear left them in the Wood, thus was the firſt exploit, the next was upon the houſe of one <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Charles</hi> of <hi>Tatnam</hi>-Court, in the Pariſh of <hi>Pancridg,</hi> where en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring his Houſe, and calling for Drink they deſired the Maſter of the houſe's Company, who refuſed to come, whereupon they concluded to call for Wine, ſaying, that no doubt would bring him; the which accordingly ſucceeded; but he no ſooner came, but one of the Company ſtarting up, asked him if he knew not <hi>Hind,</hi> to which he anſwering no, one of them with an Oath, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied that they were of his Profeſſion and wanted monies, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſome of them bound him, and the reſt went and ſeiſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Wife, his Daughter, and an old woman that lodged there, and after they had ſecured them began to plunder, but failed in their expectation for they could not meet with any thing of conſiderable vallue, yet ſeiſed ſeveral parcels of Goods to the vallue of five or ſix pounds; ſeveral of the Gang being taken and executed, the Party now the ſubject of our diſcourſe fled, but <hi>Bigs</hi> beforementioned <hi>and</hi> one <hi>Newel</hi> haveing broke the Goal of <hi>Newgate,</hi> meeting him upon their Ramble, they could not forget their old imploy, but fell to it afreſh, (ſo infatigate are thoſe ſort of people, that they can as ſoon put off them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as leave their Villanies; and after having committed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Robberies in the <hi>North</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> were returning again for <hi>London,</hi> but at <hi>St. Albans</hi> being ſuſpected for looſe perſons were apprehended and the laſt Seſſions upon their. Trials found Guilty, according to Law received the dreadful Sentance of death <hi>Bigs</hi> and <hi>Newel</hi> were executed with the other Priſoners and <hi>Pardue</hi> for ſome Reaſons reprieved till this day.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:43959:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
            <p>During the reſpited time moſt graciouſly allowed for his Repentance, and making his peace with his Creator, he behaved himſelf very reſolutely, not as a Man droping into Eternity ought, but as if grown deſperate with the ſenſe of Death he knew not what he did, yet often muſing on his preſent-State, he would ſeem ſomewhat to relent bu pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently again fall into Contempt of Life and ſtorm at thoſe that came to ſee him, ſaying that though his accuſers had taken his Life, they should not have his Soul, or words to that effect. Being asked where they had diſpoſed of the Goods they took from Mr. <hi>Benning,</hi> his anſwer was, that they were ſold by one of the Company already executed, to a party living in or near Charterhouſe-Lane but he was not at the delivery of them, and ſo could not glue any particular account, but ſaid that there was blood enough already paid for them, or to that effect, in the Morning when he was helped into the Cart he looked very chearful, but at the place of Execution when Death looked Gaſtly on him he began to change, looked pale, and deſired all preſent to take warning by his ſad end, and not be deluded or perſwaded as he had been, to cloſe with the like unlawful practices.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Gale</hi> the Broaker who received Sentence of Death with the teſt, for receiving a Stone horſe and a Mare of <hi>John Bigs,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Newel</hi> before mentioned, which they ſtole in <hi>Buckingham-ſhire,</hi> and giving them forty ſhil1lings for them, after his long Reſpit, and his great Repentance, Received his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties moſt Gracious Reprieve. And we hope this will be a warning not only to him, but to all that deal in that unlawful way that for the future they will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware how they encourage Thieves and Villains by receiving or purchaſing thoſe Goods which they by violence or fraud do take from honeſt and induſtrious men.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43959:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
